Guide to the New Leader Records TAM 271
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New Leader Records
1928-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New Leader (New York, N.Y.: 1924)
Kolatch, Myron
TAM 271
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The New Leader (1924-2006) was a socialist, then liberal, journal of opinion. Under Samuel M. (Sol) Levitas's editorship (1936-61), it gained prominence as a voice of anti-communist liberalism that featured the work of prominent intellectuals. The records contain correspondence (including some in Russian), clippings, and topical files relating to editorial and financial matters, annual dinners, radio broadcasts and other sponsored public programs, and to organizations, events and issues of interest to the editors.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Myron Kolatch, Executive Editor of the New Leader in circa 1965. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.009.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Organized into one series:
Missing Title
1. Subject Files.
Historical/Biographical Note
The New Leader(1924-2006) was the official (weekly) periodical of the Socialist Party until 1936 when, after a split in the SP, it became the official periodical of the Social Democratic Federation through 1946, after which it was published independently (including a period under the auspices of the American Labor Conference on International Affairs). It became a biweekly in 1961, and a bimonthly in 2000. Under Samuel M. (Sol) Levitas's editorship (1936-61), it gained prominence as a voice of anti-communist liberalism that featured the work of prominent intellectuals.
Sources:
Hugh Wilford, "The New Leader and the Cultural Cold War," Diplomatic History, Vol. 27, no. 1 (January 2003).
Scope and Content Note
The records contain correspondence (including some in Russian), clippings, political memoranda, and topical files relating to editorial and financial matters, annual dinners, radio broadcasts and other sponsored public programs, and to organizations, events and issues of interest to the editors, including the American Friends of Czechoslovakia, American Labor Conference on International Affairs, the American Jewish Committee, the Communist Party of Yugoslovakia, the Rand School of Social Science, and the Transport Workers Union. Notable individuals represented include Raphael Abramovitch, Jack Beall, Anton Ciliga, Fernando Gerassi, Sidney Hook, Fulton Lewis, Eugene Lyons, James Oneal, Julia Stuart Poyntz, Marc Rein and Louis Waldman (re: his resignation from American Labor Party). Also included is a manuscript by Michel Collinet, "Quarante Annees de Communisme en Europe Occidentale."
Liberalism |z United States; Socialism -- United States -- Periodicals.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Anti-communist movements -- United States.; Communism |z Europe, Eastern.; American Jewish Committee; Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; Komunistička partija Jugoslavije; Transport Workers Union of America; American Labor Conference on International Affairs; Lyons, Eugene, 1898-1985; Lewis, Fulton, 1903-1966; Levitas, Samuel M. (Sol); Collinet, Michel, 1904-. Quarante Annees de communisme en Europe occidentale.; Ciliga, Ante, 1898-1992; Beall, Jack.; Abramovitch, Raphael, b. 1880; New Leader (New York, N.Y.: 1924); Waldman, Louis, b. 1892; American Friends of Czechoslovakia; Rand School of Social Science; Oneal, James, 1875-1962; Poyntz, Julia Stuart, 1886-1937?; Kolatch, Myron
- Series 1: Subject Files
  - Abramovitch, Raphael: re: Marc Rein Case, etc. (See also file: Correspondence: In Russian), 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Friends of Czechoslovakia, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Labor Conference on International Affairs: By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Labor Conference on International Affairs: Certificate of Incorporation, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Labor Conference on International Affairs: Tax-Exempt Status, 1954, 1962-1964, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Dinners, 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Dinners, 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beall, Jack: Broadcasts, 1947, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Digest, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ciliga, Ante: Book Excerpt ("Chapter 4"), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collinet, Michel: "Quarante Annees de Communisme en Europe Occidentale" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1936-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (in Russian), 1936-1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Editorial: "Save the Rescuers", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Finances, undated, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gerassi, Fernando (report re:), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hook, Sidney: St. John's College Article (corresp. re:), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Howe, Quincy: WQXR Broadcast on Krivitsky, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Council on European Problems: "America and the Post-War World," report, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Lincoln-Petkov Academy and The National Academy Organizations: Proposal by the "Orlando Committee", ca.1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Levitas, Sol M.: Personal, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lewis, Fulton, Jr.: Radio Broadcast Transcripts, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lists of New Leader Articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lyons, Eugene, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York Herald Tribune: Editorials, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oneal, James, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Operation Survival (film): Veterans of Foreign Wars (VFW) Complaint, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Political Memoranda, undated, 1944, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Poyntz, Julia Stuart: Case (incl. misc. photos), undated, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Publicity, undated, 1933, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Radio Broadcasts re: New Leader articles, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rand School, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rubenstein, M .I.: Quotations from Articles by, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Stedman, Seymour, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sunday Leader: Perspectives, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Thomas, Lowell: Broadcast Excerpt on Pyotr Kapitsa, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Der Tog (The Day): Clipping, Registration Department, Jul 17, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Transport Workers Union: Daily Worker Clipping, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Transport Workers Union and Mike Quill: Edward Maguire Testimony re:, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Trevino, Jose (Argentinian journalist), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - United States Department of State, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Wachenheim, Hedwig, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Waldman, Louis: Resignation from American Labor Party, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - William, Maurice: Materials on Sun Yat-Sen and Chinese Politics, 1928-1940, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Yugoslav Communist Party: Letter to Stalin and Molotov, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Yugoslav Communist Party: Soviet Letters to, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)